<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Committee of Estates of the Parliament of Scotland to the honourable Houses of Parliament, and to all their brethren of England concerning the necessity, grounds, and ends of their engagement, and of the return of the Scots armie into England.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34038</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13662837</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13662837</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1047:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Committee of Estates of the Parliament of Scotland to the honourable Houses of Parliament, and to all their brethren of England concerning the necessity, grounds, and ends of their engagement, and of the return of the Scots armie into England.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Arch. Primerose.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101133:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101133:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE COMMITTEE of ESTATES Of the PARLIAMENT of SCOTLAND, TO THE Honourable Houſes of the PARLIAMENT, And to all their Brethren of ENGLAND, <hi>Concerning</hi> The Neceſſity, Grounds, and Ends of their Engagement, and of the RETURN of the <hi>SCOTS</hi> ARMIE into <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="royal_seal">
            <pb facs="tcp:101133:2"/>
            <head>GOD ſave the KING</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101133:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the COMMITTEE of the Eſtates of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> To the Honourable Houſes of the PARLIAMENT, and to all their Brethren of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter ſo long a continuance of the ſad calamities that have almoſt waſted theſe three Kingdoms, and the uninterrupted endeavours of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to have all the cauſes of them removed; We cannot poſſibly expreſſe with what grief of ſoul we find them ſtill more likely to be increaſed than diminiſhed; Neither did any part of our former ſufferings more deeply afflict us, then again to be neceſſitated to Expreſſions and Actions, that by ſome will rather be looked upon as Incentives of new troubles, then meanes to quiet and calme the preſent diſtempers. Therefore we have thought fit to offer this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing <hi>Declaration</hi> to the Honourable Houſes of Parliament, and to our Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> for ſatisfaction of all religious, loyall and honeſt men; that Heaven and Earth may beare witneſſe with us of the neceſſity of our Engagement and undertakings at this time, and of the candour of our Intentions and Reſolutions.</p>
            <p>After that by the bleſſing of God upon the endeavours of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and their Armies at home and in <hi>England</hi> in two ſeverall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditions, a happy Peace was ſetled, Religion and the juſt Liberties of this Kingdom eſtabliſhed, a Parliament called in <hi>England,</hi> and great progreſſe made towards the redreſſe of all grievances, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming abuſes both in Church and State: It pleaſed the Lord again to call us to new troubles: For the differences betwixt the King and Parliament being increaſed and heightened into a bloody War, the many Addreſſes of this Kingdom to His Majeſty and the two Houſes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101133:3"/>for an amicable compoſure of differences having proved fruitleſſe and ineffectuall, and the Parliament reduced to a low condition, This Kingdom was invited to the aſſiſtance of their Brethren, large Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions by them were made of their deſires of unity and uniformity in Religion, of a neerer conjunction with this Kingdom, and the dangers were fully repreſented to us of a prevailing Party in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> different from us in <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Church-Government:</hi> It was then acknowledged, that the ſame fate in <hi>Religion</hi> attended both: And becauſe it was well known, that although unhappy dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences had ariſen betwixt his Majeſty &amp; his Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, yet <hi>Scotland</hi> could never be drawn into any action againſt His Majeſty, or that fidelity and ſubjection which they owe to Him and his Poſterity; large profeſſions were therefore made by the two Houſes of their loyalty to their King, whoſe greatneſſe and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they profeſſed they never intended to diminiſh, as may more fully appear in the ſeverall <hi>Declarations;</hi> Commiſſioners were ſent into this Kingdom, Invitations renewed, a Treaty made, and a <hi>Covenant</hi> ſolemnly ſigned and ſworne for Reformation and defence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the honour and happineſſe of the King, and the peace and ſafety of the Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Thus both Kingdoms were equally and mutually engaged, and in purſuance of the <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Treaty</hi> an Army marched into <hi>England</hi> in the hardeſt Seaſon; and both Kingdoms in their joynt-Declaration, <hi>Jan.</hi> 6. 1643/4. obliged themſelves and decreed never to lay down Arms, till Truth and Peace by the bleſſing of God were ſetled in this Iland upon a firm foundation for the preſent and future Generations. Although we ſhall not mention what ſucceſſe that Army had, what Blood they loſt both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> what hardſhips they endured, and how much this Kingdome was thereby impoveriſhed: yet we cannot but remember, how that by the bleſſing of God upon the joynt Councels and Forces of both Kingdoms, the two Houſes of Parliament were recovered into a condition of making good thoſe Engagements, and with what unity both Kingdoms proceeded towards the attaining of thoſe Ends, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that Party in the Houſes, who ſince have declared themſelves <hi>Independents</hi> (who ſeemed forward in the engaging of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and at firſt profeſt greateſt care of our Army) had attained to power, diſcovered their intentions, and interrupted all theſe fair be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101133:3"/>They created and fomented jealouſies againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> and by their influence on the two Houſes caſhiered all in <hi>England</hi> by Sea and Land, how eminent, how faithfull ſoever, that they could not confide in; And by the ſucceſſe of their new-modelled Army, for the moſt part Sectaries, they engroſſed all power Military and Civill into their own and their Creatures hands: the Propoſitions formerly agreed on by both Kingdoms and treated on at <hi>Vxbridge,</hi> were altered; yet this Kingdom and thoſe imployed by them were content ſo far to deny themſelves and their own intereſts, as to wave the Propoſitions moſt advantagious to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and for witneſſing their deſire of Peace, to joyn in thoſe framed by the two Houſes, where the Independents had got ſuch a power: And for the greateſt teſtimony of our confidence in the Honourable Houſes of Parliament (notwithſtanding the many injuries and diſcouragements received in <hi>England</hi> from the then and ſtill prevailing party in the Engliſh Army and their Abetters, who were grown <hi>Anti-Covenanters,</hi> and threatned a diſappointment of all the Ends of the <hi>Covenant</hi>) upon the publike faith of the Houſes, given to us for the preſervation and ſafety of His Majeſties ſacred perſon, and of making joynt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to His Majeſty for ſetling a ſafe and well-grounded Peace, and free acceſſe of all imployed by this Kingdom to his Majeſty, the Armies of <hi>Scotland</hi> returned from <hi>England,</hi> and left the King with the Engliſh Commiſſioners; moſt of our Army were immediately thereafter disbanded, and no more kept on foot but ſo many as were neceſſary for reducing ſome <hi>Scots</hi> Rebels, and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> Subjects of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> (whom by the large Treaty <hi>England</hi> was bound to reduce) We expected that the like courſe would have been taken for disbanding of the Armies in <hi>England,</hi> and none kept on foot but ſuch as were neceſſary for the Garriſons and ſafety of the Kingdom, (there being then no profeſt Enemy in Arms) and thoſe to have been ſuch as both Kingdoms might have confided in, for affection to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Monarchy: whereunto the Honourable Houſes of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament did effectually apply themſelves, as appears by their <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the 28. of <hi>May</hi> 1647. But the Independent party were as diligent to hinder it; Firſt by contriving and procuring a Petition from the Army againſt their disbanding, which by the Houſes was Voted mutinous, and the Abetters of it enemies to the State, 200000 <abbr>l.</abbr> was provided and Commiſſioners ſent down to the Army for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101133:4"/>it, and engaging a conſiderable Supply for <hi>Ireland</hi> under the Command of Generall-Major <hi>Skippon,</hi> and Lieut. Generall <hi>Maſſey,</hi> 167 Presbyterian Officers engaged for <hi>Ireland</hi> and gave obedience to the commands of the Parliament: but on a ſudden, the Sectaries of that Army drew themſelves together, entred into a ſolemn En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement againſt the Reſolutions of the Parliament, caſhiered all the Prerbyterian Officers who had adhered to the Parliament or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for <hi>Inland,</hi> placed Sectaries in their Charges, erected a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Councel of <hi>Agitators,</hi> and then grew indeed into a compleat new Modell: Soon thereafter, a Party out of ſeverall Regiments, (commanded by a Tailor, a Cornet of theirs, one <hi>Joyce</hi>) violently ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed on the Perſon of the King, and carried him from his houſe at <hi>Holdenby,</hi> againſt his own will and the Proteſtation of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners then attending upon him, and againſt the declared reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of both Kingdoms: and though this action was at firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avowed by the <hi>GENERALL,</hi> yet it appears to have been done by ſome under-hand Warrant; for the King was kept ſtill within the Army's Quarters, ſtrong Guards placed about him; and when the Houſes thought fit to command the Army not to come within thirty miles of <hi>London,</hi> and to Vote his Majeſties comming to <hi>Richmond,</hi> They by threatning Meſſages forced the recalling of theſe Votes, and carried the King along with them to <hi>Hatſield</hi> and other places at their pleaſure. The Houſes did then juſtly think it neceſſary to look to their own preſervation, leſt they ſhould be ſerved as his Majeſty was: And upon the 11. of <hi>June</hi> 1647. they appointed a Committee of Safety to meet with the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and conſider upon the preſervation of the Parliament and City, the great work of the Army being to New-model the Parliament as well as they had done Themſelves, and to ſubdue and enſlave that great and glorious City: In order whereunto, they firſt began with a falſe &amp; frivolous general Charge againſt divers Members of the Houſes, eminent for affection &amp; actions in this Cauſe, and violently preſt their ſuſpenſion from the Houſe; but upon a full and free debate it was Voted to be againſt the Law, to ſuſpend any Member upon a generall Charge, without bringing in and proving of particulars. This procedure did not fit the Armies occaſions: Therefore by ſeverall threatning Meſſages, That they would march to <hi>Westminſter,</hi> That they would purge the Houſe, and that they muſt take extraordinary courſes, They
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101133:4"/>force the Houſes to recall their Votes for a Committee of ſafety, to disband what forces they had drawn together under Presbyterian Officers, they compell the eleven Members to withdraw from their attendance in the Houſe, And the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London</hi> at the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous deſire of the Common-Counſel, being then ſetled in the hands of ſuch perſons as the City might moſt conſide in, the Army to perfect their deſigns upon them, enforces the Houſes to a new modell of that <hi>Militia.</hi> Having thus in their power the Perſon of His Majeſtie, and having overawed the Parliament and City they diſperſe themſelves in the ſeverall Counties about <hi>London,</hi> liſt and raiſe daily more forces, and revolves to ſettle, or rather to alter and ſubvert <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> after their own will, as is held forth in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſalls, which they firſt preſented to His Majeſtie, and afterwards ſent them to the Houſes, as that which they would have the ground of Peace: But the City was ſo enraged at the change of the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> that they came down to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to petition againſt it, and the Prentices (who had learned from the Army the powerfulleſt Arguments to perſwade) came in multitudes and preſt the grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Common-Counſells Petition. Thus on the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> 1647, the Houſes again ſetled the <hi>Militia</hi> as formerly, many in <hi>London</hi> entered into an in Engagement, but the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London</hi> quieted all Tumults, ſetled orderly guards, and the next day the Houſe of Commons ſate quietly; yet it was reſolved by that partie that the two Speakers and the friends of the Army ſhould flie thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which they did: The Houſes notwithſtanding ſate, chooſed new Speakers, revived the Committee of ſafety, and put themſelves in a poſture of defence, and upon the deſires of the Commiſsioners of this Kingdom, they invited His Majeſtie to come to <hi>London</hi> with <hi>Honour, Freedome</hi> and <hi>Safety.</hi> The Army drew together, refuſed to own the Parliament, declared againſt them, printed their own Propoſalls, cryed out againſt a new War, And in the mean time them and their friends that lied to them, being engaged by a writing to live and die together, marched up againſt the Parliament and City, who ſeemed to have been in a readineſſe to oppoſe them, untill by the endeavours of ſome, that were better friends to the Sectaries; then to the Parliament and City, by their many adreſſes to the Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd returns, the City was ſurrendered, and the Sectaries having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought up the Speakers and Members that fled to them, marched
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101133:5"/>in triumph through <hi>London</hi> with Laurells in their hats; Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> was made Captain-Generall of all <hi>England,</hi> Conſtable of the Tower of <hi>London</hi> and Commander of all the Garriſons in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> he put out an honeſt faithfull Citizen, and put in a Sectary Livetenant of the Tower, and then they fell afreſh upon the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Houſe (as they called it) Seven Lords were impeached of a new pretended Treaſon, the eleven Members forced to flie, and after a fourtnights debate, and being often carried in the negative (for a little Liberty yet remained) At laſt by a threatning Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the Army, and the Sword-mens coming into the Houſe, all Orders paſt in abſence of the old Speakers, were repealed and ſome of the activeſt of the Houſes, the Lord Major, three honeſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vers Common-Counſellours of <hi>London</hi> charged and impriſoned, the Officers of the City altered, and all upon generall accuſations for raiſing a new War; but indeed really for being zealous for the ends of the Covenant and for defence of the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, yea the being of the Parliament, againſt the violence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence of this Shiſmatick Army.</p>
            <p>The liberty of the Parliament being thus deſtroyed by their own Servants, contrary to their many profeſsions, the famous City of <hi>London</hi> enſlaved to Sectaries, and not onely thoſe priviledges taken from them, which by their faithfulneſſe to the Parliament, and with the expenſe of ſo much Blood and Treaſure they had merited, but even their ancient Liberties troaden on, and all things governed at <hi>Weſtminiſter</hi> and <hi>London</hi> according to order from the Court of War, who alſo by a raigning ſpirit of <hi>Levelling Democraty,</hi> were, or ſeemed to be over-ruled be the new-ſupreme Counſell of Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators, who had been Souldiers and now were turned ſuperlative Commanders: As the labour of the <hi>Independant Junto,</hi> was to court the people and the ſouldiery by Declarations and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (which they aſſoon falcified) and even to trade with the <hi>Papiſts</hi> (as was informed) ſo they ſtudied to intereſt the Kings party, and cajolled ſome of them to purpoſe that were moſt obnoxtious to the Parliament, and excepted in the Propoſitions: But they ſoon manifeſted to the World, what their intentions were to the King, for after they had made uſe of the detaining of His Majeſties Perſon in their Army, and of pretending for His intereſts and partie to enable them to ſubdue the Parliament and City; That
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101133:5"/>work being over, they firſt grew ſeverer to His party (except ſuch as they ſtill made very good uſe of) and then endeavoured by threatening to fright him away from <hi>Hampton-Court;</hi> The power of the Levellers was much talked of untill His Majeſtie was ſure in the <hi>Ile</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> and then their Lievetenant-Generall found a means to quiet them: In the <hi>Ile</hi> of <hi>Wight</hi> they firſt made His Majeſtie Priſoner, without any known authority, and then got the Houſes to own and order it, And by the prevalency of the <hi>Independant</hi> party, Votes were paſt making another kind of new high Treaſon, to make any application to the King, to write to him, or receive letters from him (a ſeverity greater then is uſuall againſt malefactors) and for juſtifying of theſe votes, a Declaration was publiſhed, with many falſe ſcandals caſt upon his Majeſty, and it is even declared they will put no more truſt in his Majeſty, yea now we are informed, that by horrid treachery and poyſon, endeavours are uſed to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his life.</p>
            <p>As that Independent party, hath endeavoured to ſubvert the begunne Reformation of Religion, to deſtroy the King and Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and overthrow the Parliament, and perſecute honeſt men, ſo it hath been their ſtudy even ſince the removall of the Scots Army, to break the happy union betwixt the kingdomes, to lay aſide the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, diſappoint all the ends of it, and violate all treaties betwixt the kingdomes; we ſhall not need to repeat the jealouſies they crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and fomented againſt <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Scots Commiſſioners; and our Army, whilſt it was there, how they withheld the maintenance from them due by the Treaty, that by free quarters they might grow burthenſome and odious to the people, nor need we now to mention any violation of the large Treaty concerning the remainder of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney due upon the Brotherly aſſiſtance, nor of the money due by Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for our Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or by the late Treaty upon the march of our Army; nor ſhall We now inſiſt on the Breach of that Article of the large Treaty, by which the Houſes were obliged to purſue, take, and puniſh the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, Subjects of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> who ſo long infeſted us: We have already declared what Breaches they have made of the ſolemn engagements for the King, and when our Commiſſioners at London demanded whither the votes againſt all application to his Majeſty, did extend to his Subjects of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to debarre ſuch as are warranted by the Parliament of this kingdome,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101133:6"/>or their Committes from free acceſſe to, or intercourſe with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or that he ſhould be hindred from, and ſo made incapable of any Act of Government, in relation to the Affairs of <hi>Scotland?</hi> No An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was then nor as yet is returned thereunto, but before that time, not only ſuch as had warrants for acceſſe to him were debar'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, notwithſtanding of the engagement of the Houſe 27. of <hi>January</hi> 1647. to the contrary; But even the Earle of <hi>Lawderdaill</hi> a publick Miniſter of this kingdom, contrary to that engagement, and to the Law of Nations, was violently removed by a party of the Army from <hi>Woburn,</hi> where his Majeſty then was, and not ſuffered to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to him, and though reparation was therein deſired by the laſt Committee of Eſtates, yet none was given; And although by the 8. Article of the Treaty 1643. It is agreed that no ceſſation, pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor agreement for peace whatſoever ſhall be made by either kingdome, or the Armies of either kingdomes, without the mutuall advice and conſent of both kingdomes, which engagement the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament alſo repeated in their letter of the 27. of <hi>January</hi> 1647. to obſerve that Article after the removall of our Army out of <hi>England;</hi> yet contrary thereunto the Sectaries and their adherents framed propoſals deſtructive to the ends of the Covenant, which were preſented to his Majeſty without the advice or conſent of the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and having cunningly inſerted therein ſome things more pleaſing to his Majeſty, then the propoſitions of both kingdomes were, it was their ſtudy to perſwade his Majeſty in his anſwer to the Propoſitions at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> to throw himſelfe on the propoſals, and thereby unſatisfy both his kingdomes, which as ſoon as the King had done, they themſelves laid them aſide and uſed his Majeſty as we have before expreſt. And whereas the Houſes of Parliament, whilſt in liberty, made it their work, firſt to disband the Army, before any applications to be made to his Majeſty, the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Army having the King within the quarters of their Army, and the City reduced, preſt vehemently the ſending of the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of both, kingdoms, whilſt themſelves were faſteſt trinketing with their Propoſals; a ſhort and peremptory day: was ſet for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Propoſitions, without the advice or conſent of the Commiſſioners of the kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> then at <hi>London;</hi> and Inſtructions given, That if the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners were not there preſent at that day, the Propoſitions nevertheleſſe ſhould be delivered
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101133:6"/>without them: And as we have great reaſon to believe, that it was the ſtudy of the Sectaries and thoſe that were their Inſtruments in that Treaty, that His Majeſty ſhould not ſatisfie his Parliaments by his Anſwer; yet upon that Anſwer, by the power and prevalencie of that Party, the Houſes of Parliament laid aſide the Propoſitions agreed on by both Kingdoms, and have (contrary to the Treaty) framed and preſented Propoſitions and Bills to His Majeſty, againſt which the Commiſſioners of this Kingdom declared, and thereafter by order according to their Inſtructions proteſted againſt them in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> as being deſtructive to Religion, the Crown, and union of the Kingdoms, as may at large be ſeen in that printed Anſwer to the new Propoſitions, which the Parliament here have owned and approved as the ſenſe of this Kingdom, and which we hold as here repeated:</p>
            <p>The Parliament of this Kingdom taking into their conſideration the dangers thus threatning Religion, His Majeſties ſacred Perſon and Poſterity, yea Monarchy and all Government; how that by the injuſtice, violence and treachery of the Independents and their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents in Parliament and Army, the Covenant was laid aſide, all the ends of it fruſtrated, <hi>Toleration</hi> countenanced and by the new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions endeavoured to be ſetled, His Majeſty impriſoned and ſuch height of inſolencies committed againſt him, The priviledges, yea the being of the Parliament being in a manner deſtroyed, and the foundations of it razed, The famous City of <hi>London</hi> (to whom this Nation and all that are faithfull in this Cauſe muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo great obligations) enſlaved, its Liberties troden on, and many of the beſt affected to the Covenant, in Parliament and City, for their fidelity perſecuted and driven away, The Treaties with and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to this Nation broken, The publike Faith of <hi>England,</hi> yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all Laws divine and humane violated, The people of <hi>England</hi> oppreſt with Free-Quarter and Taxes, and the union and brotherly correſpondence betwixt the Kingdoms much weakened and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be taken away; And being very ſenſible of the many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and affronts done to this Nation, their Army, and thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by them; weighing alſo well how fruitleſſe all their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours by way of Treaty and Meſſages for curing thoſe evils and removing thoſe differences had proven, and how little regard was had to our Commiſſioners and their endeavours at <hi>London</hi> of late,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101133:7"/>Thought it high time to look to their own preſervation, and to put this Kingdom into a poſture of Arms. Yet before any further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, they reſolved to try, if by the Three juſt and neceſſary Demands of the 26. of <hi>Aprill</hi> made to the Houſes of Parliament, it were poſſible in an amicable way to compoſe thoſe differences and provide for the ſecurity of Religion, of His Majeſty, and of the peace and union of the Kingdoms: To the which had a ſatisfactory An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer been returned, all the Inconveniencies that may enſue, might have been prevented, which we have ſtill ſince that time patiently expected.</p>
            <p>But in ſtead of ſecurity to Religion according to the Covenant againſt the dangers on all hands; In ſtead of freeing His Majeſty from his baſe impriſonment, that he may come to ſome of his houſes in or neer <hi>London</hi> with Honour, Freedom and Safety, where both Kingdoms may make their applications to him for ſetling Religion and a well-grounded Peace; In ſtead of disbanding the Army of Sectaries, by whoſe power and tyrannie all thoſe evils are come upon us, and further threaten us, without taking any notice at all of what upon ſo juſt and neceſſary grounds we demanded, without any reparation given of the many injuries done to this Kingdome and thoſe imployed by them, or any Anſwer to that demand made by our Commiſſioners, Whether it was intended that His Majeſty ſhould bee debarred from exerciſing any act of Government in relation to this Kingdom, Or whether Scots men imployed and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by <hi>Scotland</hi> might have free acceſſe to him: In ſtead (we ſay) of all theſe, we have received three Propoſitions to be preſented to His Majeſty, that after His Majeſty aſſent thereto, and to ſuch Acts of Parliament as ſhall be offered by both Houſes for confirmation thereof, then both Houſes will treat with his Majeſty, (without tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him or us, where or with what ſecurity to either) concerning the future ſettlement of the Government of the Church, and the ſettlement of the <hi>Militia,</hi> and the reſt of the Propoſitions formerly tendered at <hi>Hampton-Court;</hi> And a deſire from the Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners reſiding here, for us to prepare ſuch Propoſitions as we ſhall judge fit and neceſſary for this Kingdom, that they may be ſent to His Majeſty with all convenient ſpeed: They did alſo commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate to us ſome Votes of the two Houſes; and the Committee of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates told them, That they could return no Anſwer, till firſt they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101133:7"/>ſatisfaction to the Demands of this Kingdom of the 26. of <hi>April,</hi> And theſe are as little ſatisfied, Religion, the King and his Kingdoms as little ſecured, and the ſolid grounds of a Religious and good Peace, as little provided for now as formerly.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not much inſiſt on the particulars of theſe three Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Our Commiſſioners did on ſome of them ſo fully expreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, eſpecially that of the <hi>Militia,</hi> in their late Anſwer to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, before they went to the Ile of <hi>Wight</hi> (which we here hold as repeated) But we cannot conceale, how very unſatisfactory that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Religion</hi> is; and we are ſorry to ſee other Intereſts ſtill ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully provided for, and ſo little ſecurity to Religion, which indeed was the main and principall cauſe of our Engagement in the late warres. In theſe Propoſitions we ſtill find the <hi>Covenant</hi> omitted, one end of it only mentioned by way of Narrative, and the Propoſitions for Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity according to the Covenant, with all the other Propoſitions of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion left to the future Treaty, and all that is now deſired, is, That Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Government be confirmed by Act of Parliament in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as both Houſes of Parliament have agreed in ſeverall Ordinances of Parliament, That is to ſay, &amp;c. The Commiſſioners of the Parliament and Generall Aſſembly of this Kingdome have ſeverall times expreſt their ſenſe of theſe Ordinances, which we ſhall not here repeat: But we doubt this new <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be of a larger extent, and relates to that impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Toleration</hi> ſetled by both Houſes, ſo contrary to Covenant, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the ends of it, and for ought we know not yet repealed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which this Kingdom hath ſo fully declared in the forementioned Anſwer to the new Propoſitions: for it was then brought in as a part of the Propoſition for ſetling Presbyteriall Government, as the way that both the Houſes then agreed to: And ſeeing the ſame over-awing power continues, which firſt brought in that <hi>Toleration</hi> avowedly, we have reaſon to apprehend it ſtill remains, but is now covered &amp; rolled up in this new <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And we have the greater reaſon to be unſatisfied, that Presbyteriall Government is only demanded for three years, and in the end of the Propoſitions it is profeſſed, that the Houſes will treat with his Majeſty concerning the future ſettlement of the Government of the Church, without relating to the Covenant as a rule of the Government, or the Propoſitions formerly agreed upon by both Kingdoms, but in ſuch a generall as may overthrow all the Reformation eſtabliſhed, and open a door to Hierarchy or Anarchy, to Epiſcopacie or Independencie,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101133:8"/>and to <hi>Toleration,</hi> All abjured in our ſolemn Covenant.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing no ſatisfaction is given to the ſo juſt &amp; neceſſary demands of the Parliament of the 26 of April, either for Religion or the Kings Majeſty, but that Religion is ſtill in as much hazard as ever, the King ſtill barbarouſly detained in his baſe impriſonment, and as we are cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly informed, daily in hazard of his life by Treachery and Poyſon, and that Army of Sectaries (the great cauſe of all our evills and dangers) ſtill kept up, ſtrengthned, and a great part of it now marched cloſe to our Border: Though this Kingdome ſhall never be averſe from giving and receiving mutuall ſatisfaction by Treaty; yet we cannot agree to theſe Propoſitions, nor joyn with the two Houſes in preſenting of them to His Majeſty, whilſt neither King nor Parliament enjoy their liberties. THEREFOR we can no longer, as unconcerned ſpectators, be witneſſes to the loſſe and ruine of all, which by the oath of God that lies upon us in our ſolemn League and Covenant, and by many other obligations, we are bound to endeavour to preſerve: And the ends being now the ſame for which we were invited, and in proſecution whereof we loſt ſo much Blood, did undergoe ſo many hardſhips, and ſo much impoveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed our own country, and being engaged by the joynt Declaration of both kingdomes, never to lay down Armes, till Truth and Peace be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Iland, upon a firm foundation for the preſent, and future Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, being alſo invited thereunto by many of that kingdom joyned in Covenant with us. Our forces are again in <hi>England,</hi> and in diſcharge of our duties to God, our Native King, our own country, and our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>England,</hi> we have undertaken this ſo neceſſary engagement, in proſecution of thoſe juſt, pious and loyall ends, to which we are ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſworn. And although we have not at all departed from our good old Principles, and that our Demands and Deſires are contained in our ſeverall Declarations, Papers, and addreſſes this time paſt to the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, yet ſeeing by the malice of our enemies, many falſe and ſcandalous aſperſions are caſt upon us, our Actions and intentions traduced, and jealouſies raiſed in the minds of many good (though too credulous) men both at home annd abroad; for ſatisfaction of all that are ſatisfiable, and to witneſſe the ſincerity of our intentions and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we ſhall here repeat our moſt material deſires, and the grounds of our undertakings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We declare before God and all the world, that we are reſolved ſincerely, really &amp; conſtantly, to maintain and preſerve inviolably with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101133:8"/>the hazard of our Lives and Fortunes, and all that is deareſt unto us the Reformation of Religion, in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it is by the mercy of God, and his Majeſties goodneſſe eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by Law amongſt us; and never to ſuffer it by fraud or force to be taken from us, nor yet to endure the bringing in of Epiſcopacy, the Book of Common Prayer, or any other of theſe Innovations and Superſtitions, thrown out of this Church, (as ſome have bin ſo impudent to averre) And alſo with the ſame ſincerity, reality, and conſtancy, in our places and callings, to the uttermoſt of our power faithfully to endeavour the confirming what is already done in the work of Reformation, eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Covenant, and attaining all the ends of it in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> particularly Reformation of Religion and Uniformity according to the Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We doe alſo declare that we will endeavour the Reſcue of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Perſon from his baſe impriſonment, that he may come with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Freedome and Safety to ſome of his own Houſes in or near Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, that the Parliaments of both kingdomes may make their applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to him for obtaining his Royall Aſſent to ſuch deſires as ſhal be by them preſented to him, for eſtabliſhing Religion as is above expreſt; and ſetling a well-grounded Peace, that ſo his Majeſty may live in the Splendor and Glory of his Royall Progenitours, as beſeemeth his Royall Place and Dignity. That all differences and troubles may end in mutuall confidence and rejoycing, the King may enjoy the comfort of his Royall Conſort and children, with other contentments. And We af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo great diſtractions and long continued ſufferings may reap the bliſſed fruits of Truth and Peace under his Government. For however the late procedure of this kingdome, may have been miſunderſtood, yet God knowes that we have never admitted of any thoughts to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of our Gracious Soveraign, his Perſon and Government, to whom we pray that the Lord would grant a long and happy Reign, and that there may not want one of his ſeed to rule over us rightly, and to ſit upon his Throne, while the Sun and the Moon endureth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the two Houſes of Parliament may be reſtored to their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that all Members who have been faithfull to this Cauſe, may freely and ſafely attend their charges; That the Parliament being Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their own Counſels and Reſults, they may together with the advice and conſent of the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> conclude in a Treaty with his Majeſty, all other things expedient to a thorough ſetlement.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101133:9"/>
            <p n="4">4. That the City of London, which hath expended ſo much in Blood and Treaſure, may have their former Propoſitions preſented to the King at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and preſt as was formerly intended.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the Army of Sectaries under the command of <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Lord <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> of Camron be disbanded, and none employed either in relation to the proſecution of the War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or the neceſſary Garriſons and forces, but ſuch as have or ſhall take the Covenant, and are well affected to Religion and Government, that ſo the people of <hi>England</hi> may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of taxes, free quarter, and other great Impoſitions under which they have ſo long groaned.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And although the intereſt of Religion, King and Kingdoms, and the ſetling of a ſolid Peace, be the cauſe of this undertaking: yet we do not doubt but due regard will be had to the concernments of <hi>Scotland</hi> contained in our ſeverall former demands, both in relation to what is due to this Kingdom and their Armies here and in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as alſo what is neceſſary for the better ſafety, union and Government of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</p>
            <p>We have now expreſt the true grounds and reaſons of this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and the Ends we propoſe to our ſelves. And we doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that none, who will not declare themſelves Enemies to God, the King, the Parliament, and peace of theſe kingdomes, will oppoſe us in this ſo pious and neceſſary an undertaking: And therefore wee hope all jealouſies and miſunderſtandings w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be laid aſide, and that we ſhall meet with a hearty concurrence, both of all the Subjects of this kingdom and our Brethren of <hi>England.</hi> And we doe declare, That it ſhall be our endeavour to protect in their perſons and goods, all of the Engliſh Nation, who ſhall joyn in Covenant with us, and for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of thoſe Ends: and that we doe no prejudice nor uſe violence to none (as farre as we are able) but ſuch as oppoſe us or thoſe Ends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned. Particularly we ſhall endeavour, that the Arrears due to all Souldiers who have ſerved the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in this Cauſe (excepting ſuch as have engaged and abetted the Army in their courſes, and ſhall not immediately deſert them) may have their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts audited, part of the Arrears payed, and ſecurity for the reſt with full indempnity.</p>
            <p>And becauſe our Army will be neceſſitated to live upon the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, untill a Regular courſe be taken for their maintenance: Wee doe declare, that it ſhall be our care, that they carry themſelves as ſoberly,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101133:9"/>and be as little burthenſome as is poſſible; and before we return, we ſhall labour to ſee the Northern Counties ſatisfied for what extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary burthens they ſuſtain.</p>
            <p>To conclude, We declare before God and the world, That we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve by Gods aſſiſtance in all our proceedings never to break on our parts the union betwixt the kingdomes, nor to encroach upon the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall rights of the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> or entrench upon their juſt Liberties: much leſſe is it our intention at all to make a Nationall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engagement againſt the Parliament and kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> but for them, whoſe freedome, priviledges, and happineſſe, ſhall ever be as dear to us as our own; And our deſires being provided for and ſecured, then immediately our Army ſhall depart the kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and return peaceably home again; whereof we have twice already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven real teſtimonies, our intentions being ever the ſame with our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions, reſolving ſtill to continue ſtedfaſt in the proſecution of them, for the accompliſhment whereof we ſhall be ready to ſacrifice both our Lives and Fortunes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ARCH. PRIMEROSE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
